<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Five Computers</title><link href="http://fivecomputers.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://fivecomputers.com/feeds/07.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://fivecomputers.com/</id><updated>2009-07-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>learning guitar with Garageband</title><link href="http://fivecomputers.com/learning-guitar-with-garageband.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-07-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>GordonMcGregor</name></author><id>tag:fivecomputers.com,2009-07-11:learning-guitar-with-garageband.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://fivecomputers.typepad.com/.a/6a00e54efca38e88340128756200ad970c-pi" width="883" height="149" alt="rocky_racoon.band.jpg" style="margin-top:0px; margin-right:0px; margin-bottom:0px; margin-left:0px; padding-top:0px; padding-right:0px; padding-bottom:0px; padding-left:0px;" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've just recently started trying to learn to play guitar. My early experiences with music would be best described as making a bad noise,on the recorder. Still, I've decided to give it another go. One thing I've found early on that playing along to a metronome really helps with keeping time, but it isn't the most interesting thing to listen to. To liven things up a little, I've been playing around with Garageband on my Mac. This is an application that comes with the iLife suite and is preinstalled on most mac's. I suspect many owners don't use it for much, other than maybe making the odd iPhone ringtone (&lt;a href="http://lifehacker.com/334073/create-custom-iphone-ringtones-the-free-and-apple-way"&gt;you can make them for free with Garageband, rather than paying money to get them in iTunes&lt;/a&gt;). Garageband also comes with several free lessons built in that are useful, if a bit limited. I've been using it mostly to record my practices and provide backing rhythm for my practice time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of playing along to the metronome, I've been making up &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Click_track"&gt;click tracks&lt;/a&gt; to play to. These are simple drum loops that I use as a backing beat. It is easy to change the tempo of the drum beat and make it loop indefinitely. I've found &lt;a href="http://www.thegaragedoor.com/tutorials/clicktracks.html"&gt;free loops&lt;/a&gt; and there are also several vanilla loops that ship with GarageBand that are useful for click tracks (such as Straight Up Beat 01). I just choose the one that has the closest feel to the rhythm I'm trying to play, then drag the loop into the main display. You can extend the loop by dragging the top right hand corner of the track out to the right. After that is done, set a cycle region to loop over the number of bars that you want it to play for and play along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the nicest features of Garageband is the ability to retime any of the loops to a given tempo, so I can start out slow and build to a faster beat, without having to change the basic arrangements of backing tracks. I can add more software instruments as I go, but for now I've been keeping things quite simple. I have played some of the melodies on the musical score editor, so that I can hear how things should sound and have that playing quietly under the track as I play along. You can also drag in tunes straight from iTunes and have those as backing tracks as well. These can also be retimed and slowed down (&lt;a href="http://www.officecafe.com/blog/2009/01/using-garageband-to-transpose-a-song-imported-from-itunes/"&gt;control-option-G is the secret undocumented&lt;/a&gt; shortcut you'll need)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://fivecomputers.typepad.com/.a/6a00e54efca38e88340120a6613708970b-pi" width="569" height="310" alt="System-2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been helpful so far. I've also started recording my attempts on a separate track (I've got an acoustic-electric guitar, so I can hook it straight into the computer). Listening to it I can hear the mistakes, but I can also pull up waveforms and visually see just where and when I was off beat. That's helped me start to tighten things up. I've been impressed by the features available in this free suite of tools. Certainly not as all encompassing as &lt;a href="http://www.apple.com/logicstudio/"&gt;Logic Studio&lt;/a&gt; or Pro Tools, but more than I need to be able to help me learn more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few days of this, I realised the biggest problem was having to hit a key to start things recording, then quickly grab the guitar and get ready to play. Garageband will provide a 4 beat count in, but that isn't really enough for me to get ready and away from the keyboard. I found an interesting solution, where I worked out how to use my iPhone to remotely control GarageBand, using the Open Sound Control protocol and some free GUI creation tools and a bit of python scripting. More about that later.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="posttagsblock"&gt;&lt;a href="http://technorati.com/tag/OSX" rel="tag"&gt;OSX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category></entry><entry><title>viigo</title><link href="http://fivecomputers.com/viigo.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-07-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>GordonMcGregor</name></author><id>tag:fivecomputers.com,2008-07-11:viigo.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've had a &lt;a href="http://www.blackberry.com/blackberrycurve.shtml"&gt;Blackberry Curve&lt;/a&gt; for a while. Really like having a real keyboard and the screen is big enough to actually browse web pages on and read quite a bit of text. However, the built-in web browser is about the worst I've ever used. Slow, clunky, painful. I have been using Google Reader's mobile view to catch up on RSS feeds and blogs while out and about. A few days ago I downloaded the free &lt;a href="http://viigo.com/home"&gt;Viigo&lt;/a&gt; feed reader. A huge improvement! Heartily recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setup was a painful, as their web site wasn't particularly fast or flexible to edit feeds. Once I realised you could download an &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OPML"&gt;OMPL&lt;/a&gt; format list from Google reader and upload it to Viigo things went much more smoothly. You can also link it directly to an aggregator feed, such as Google reader. This then keeps track of feeds that you add or remove from the other viewer, but it doesn't sync up what was read between each view, which would be a really nice feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than the setup issues, I've found it great to use. Clean interface, fast and without the pain of being in the browser environment. The price is good too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="software"></category><category term="thingumyjigs"></category></entry></feed>